The
penultimate דף ס daf samech בכורות Bechorot and we pick up the
very top of ס עמוד א samech amud aleph רבא's Rava statement
that when you are coming to do your מעשר, maaser, if you
have 15, what do you do? So he says don't take 10
and just do it on them. You have to put all 15
in the pen. רש"י Rashi says particularly don't choose the worst 10,
but part of the point also seems to be even maybe I
presume even if you wanted to choose the best 10, the idea
is that you have to take מעשר maaser over all of your
flock and they all have to be randomized, you know, and you're
not supposed to be selecting. So they all have to be in
the pen.
The other חידוש chiddush of רבא Rava was don't think that you
can leave five, the five that were not part of the process,
you can ignore them. If it's not yet ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
they have to combine with anything else that's born and then you're
going to take for the next year. Now let's take a look
at that in the... so we're going to say the same thing
from a ברייתא, braita, last line on נט עמוד ב. nun tet
amud bet. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly: היו
לו חמישה עשר טלאים, Hayu lo chamishah asar tlamim,
if he had 15 sheep, לא יאמר, lo yomar, don't say, אברור
עשרה ואטול מהן אחד והשאר פטורים, evror asarah ve-etom mehen echad ve-hashar
pturim,
let me take 10, take one, the rest I'll ignore, the rest
will be exempt. So those are two points. Number one is you
start with 10 and number two is that the five you assume
you're totally off the hook for. Don't say that. אלא כונסן לדיר,
Ela konasom ladir, put them all in the pen, ומוציא עשרה, umotzi
asarah, and 10 walk out the door, ונוטל מהן אחד, venoteil mehen
echad, and one you take, והשאר מצטרף לגורן אחר, vehashar mitztaref legoren
acher, and the other have to combine with the next... with the
next. Now רש"י Rashi says, what is... רש"י Rashi is bothered because
what is the הוה אמינא hava amina that you could ignore the
other five? If you remember, we taught an earlier משנה mishna that
if you have five from one גורן goren and five from the
other גורן, goren, they combine. So we already knew that if you
have less than 10, you're not off the hook with them, they
have to combine with anything else that's born.
You said that other משנה mishna is only when you
started with five and not with... maybe, maybe, but I'll tell you
what רש"י Rashi says.
So anyway, so we already knew that you're not off the hook
until it becomes ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, but anything else that's born
combines with any leftover. So רש"י Rashi says, so you know, right,
because right, maybe he's just repeating that point or maybe it's a
point that he... that it's different if you didn't have enough as
opposed to you had enough and there was a remainder. But רש"י
Rashi makes even a bigger חידוש. chiddush. By the way, I must
say, I haven't mentioned it and I didn't actually look into it,
but as you might have noticed in this פרק, perek, the pages
are smaller because there's this other רש"י Rashi here, רש"י כתב יד.
Rashi Ksav Yad. I should have looked into what the story is
with that. I don't know whether it's two editions of רש"י, Rashi,
whether there's a question about which one is authentic. I will tell
you that the רש"י Rashi that is not כתב יד, Ksav Yad,
the standard רש"י Rashi up here, is definitely more verbose than רש"י
Rashi usually is. So it could just be it was an earlier
draft, but maybe there is some question as to... in terms of
the authorship.
I'll have to look, I mean, I can tell you I have
a book, the best book about the standard scholarship around questions about
sort of the... what the current academic sort of take is on
all these issues about the גמרא Gemara and so on, is Strack
and Stemberger's book about Introduction to... I forgot what it's called, Introduction
to Talmud, but it's really
got... it's a distillation of all of the scholarship on all these
issues. Anyway, moving on, what רש"י Rashi says is that the חידוש
chiddush is that if they were there and it became the גורן,
goren, remember what's the basic הלכה halacha of the גורן, goren, other
than establishing that this is, you know, the regular, you know, the
times you're supposed to take, is that once you hit that time
of the גורן, goren, you're not allowed to benefit and eat from
it until you take מעשר. maaser. So רש"י Rashi actually says, and
this is not in the גמרא Gemara at all, but this is
what he reads into the חידוש chiddush of רבא, Rava, is that
if those 15 were all together, not just what the משנה mishna
says that the leftover five combine with the next five, since it
hit a גורן, goren, you can't benefit from those five because they
hit the גורן goren until you combine them with the next גורן
goren and you get מעשר. maaser. Wait, wait, even if it hit
a גורן, goren, you have... it's 15 days before פסח Pesach or
whatever, it's פרוס הפסח, pros ha-Pesach, you put all these 15 animals
together, you take מעשר, maaser, you have five left over. Those five
you cannot, because they hit a גורן, goren, you cannot שחט shacht
them or benefit from them or do any... sell them until now
right before שבועות Shavuot when you're going to combine them with a
גורן. goren. Even though you put all 15... even though you put
all 15. That's what רש"י Rashi reads in. Now it's not in
the גמרא, Gemara, so I said it's a big חידוש, chiddush, but
רש"י Rashi is bothered that isn't this idea that the leftovers combine
already in the משנה mishna and therefore he introduces this other חידוש,
chiddush, but you know, it's not... it's not at all in the
גמרא. Gemara.
Does רבא Rava say anything about that?
No. Alright, so that's the point. Now we go on.
Question: Yes. Last time we talked about the idea maybe you can
like mentally count them, maybe that's good enough. If you're looking into
your... into your corral and seeing how many are left, do I
have to bother counting them? Then you're counting them.
Right, that's true. Well, the fact that you are mentally counting them,
it's not like the איסור issur to count Jews or whatever.
It's the fact about whether that counting counts as the act of
doing מעשר. maaser. So what exactly is your question? So you've done
10, you give a quick look, you say... it doesn't look like...
oh, there's 10 there, or you count them in your head and
you see nine.
If you count them but there weren't 10, then it's not...
I guess your question is if you counted them... actually looked like
nine and you counted them and there was ten because one was
hiding and you didn't see it, does that automatically become מעשר maaser
if you're not intending for it to be מעשר? maaser? Right, I
mean, that's questions about the whole concept.
If you count them and there's only nine, then there's
no מניין הראוי, minyan harauy, it's not a nothing. Yes.
So גורן goren is really a period as opposed to any...
גורן goren is a specific date. We had the list of those
dates in the previous משנה. mishna. Yeah, exactly, exactly.
So if you have nine at one גורן, goren, you can't tithe
from any of them until you add to them.
That's what רש"י Rashi says. Now again, it's not in any גמרא,
Gemara, but רש"י, Rashi, wherever this רש"י Rashi is, is trying, is
saying, well what's the חידוש? chiddush? We already know you have to
wait, and he introduces this idea. But again, that's not in the
גמרא. Gemara. Now, the other thing I wanted to say, now that
we're just mentioning this, though, about yesterday's דף daf or two days
ago, I forget,
this whole, remember though that תוספות, Tosafot, somebody was asking me a
שאלה shaila about what that תוספות Tosafot at the מוצא motza of
that תוספות Tosafot about was about the עומר omer that you can
do it like estimating and someone was talking about that aspect for
the מעשר maaser of grain. But there was one point that I
failed to mention, which he does tie it in, because תוספות's Tosafot's
question was why the גמרא, Gemara, since you mentioned the mentally counting,
why the גמרא Gemara was bringing in that idea of estimating when
the issue of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yossi Berabbi Yehuda seemed
more to be the difference of one-tenth rather than the tenth in
a sequence. And תוספות Tosafot has a very interesting point that I
forgot to mention. That תוספות Tosafot says the following. He says, if
you're doing the tenth in a sequence, it doesn't have to be
ten percent. But as soon as, because the whole point is it's
the tenth in a sequence. But as soon as רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה Rabbi Yossi Berabbi Yehuda says you can just pick one out
of ten and you don't have to count it as number ten,
so then conceptually it's about being ten percent. But it's not ten
percent, because any one animal out of ten is going to be
a little bigger, a little smaller than the average. It's not exactly
going to be ten percent. So he says once רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה Rabbi Yossi Berabbi Yehuda introduces the idea that it's not tenth
of a sequence but ten percent, he has to link it to
מעשר דגן maaser dagan and these other things which and introduce the
idea that it can be estimate, it doesn't have to be a
precise ten percent. So I thought that was a very brilliant point.
I wanted to share that. Okay, so now we go on, which
really points out that there are two models, right? The tenth and
ten percent. Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, ותניא, ve-tanya, the גמרא Gemara says don't we teach in a
ברייתא? braita?
תשעה עשר טלאים, tishah asar telaim, if you have nineteen sheep, לא
יאמר lo yomar ever, עשרה ואטול מהן אחד, asarah ve-etol mehen echad,
I'll just, you know, take ten, put ten together and take one,
והשאר פטורין, ve-hashar peturin, the rest are exempt. אלא כונסן לדיר, ela
konesan le-dir, you put all nineteen in the pen, ומוציא עשרה u-motzi
asarah and you take ten, ונוטל מהן אחד ve-notel mehen echad and
you take one out of the ten, והשאר פטורין, ve-hashar peturin, but
the leftover nine are exempt. So here it says, you know, we
thought a minute ago I was talking about like isn't it self-evident
that the remainder are obligated? Here the ברייתא braita actually says that
the remainder are exempt. So how do you reconcile this? So the
גמרא Gemara says, תרגמה רב הונא בר סחורה קמיה דרבא בריגלא. targemah
Rav Huna bar Sechorah kamei de-Rava be-rigla. So רב הונא בר סחורה
Rav Huna bar Sechorah explained this in front of רבא. Rava. This
was רבא's Rava's statement, right, that this idea that the leftover are
obligated. This was a ברייתא braita that was a challenge to רבא.
Rava. And now apparently in the presence of רבא, Rava, רב הונא
בר סחורה Rav Huna bar Sechorah came up with an answer. So
and it says בריגלא, be-rigla, which means like on the רגל regel
or on the period right before the רגל regel when they're דרשן-ing
darshan-ing the הלכות halachot of the חג. chag. Now obviously that's interesting
because we just learned that the הלכות halachot of מעשר בהמה maaser
behemah applies right in that period before the רגל. regel. So it
seems that if, you know, probably ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, there's too
much about פסח Pesach stuff to talk about, but maybe ערב שבועות
Erev Shavuot there's not enough to talk about so you talk about
מעשר בהמה. maaser behemah. I don't know. But anyway, so it seems
like one of the things they learned before the רגל regel because
that was exactly the time was מעשר בהמה. maaser behemah. So they
were having this דרשה, drasha, this challenge was raised and to רבא,
Rava, and רב הונא בר סחורה Rav Huna bar Sechorah had an
answer. And here's what his answer was. בדיר שיש לו שני פתחים
עסקינן. be-dir she-yesh lo shenei petachim askinan. We're talking that there are
two doors. Remember that scenario yesterday? And there are nineteen animals. And
what happened? ויצאו תשעה בפתח זה ותשעה בפתח זה. ve-yatze'u tishah be-petach
zeh ve-tishah be-petach zeh. Nine went out of one door, nine went
out of the other door. Exactly the scenario we were imagining yesterday.
דהאי חד דחזי להכא ולהכא. de-hai chad de-chazi le-hacha u-le-hacha. The last
one remaining
can combine either way. So therefore, right, this was the point. When
nine went out of each door, each one is פטור במניין הראוי.
patur be-minyan harauy. Right, remember that from yesterday? Right, so each nine
that went out, since there was one left, it could have gone
out either door, so each nine that went out could have been
part of a process of ten. And therefore when we say the
remaining nine are exempt, we don't mean the remaining nine that were
left in the pen, we mean the nine that went out of
the other door. It's a bit of a stretch, of course, because
the ברייתא braita just says the remaining nine, but we're saying, creative
answer, the nine went out of a different door and it was
פטור patur because of מניין הראוי. minyan harauy. Now, by the way,
I should mention that Michael asked the question yesterday, which is if
you have one left, when רבא Rava says that the tenth one
is מברר mevarer itself, if it's obviously tenth, it automatically becomes tenth.
What if it's obviously tenth but you don't know which tenth it
is? Is it the tenth of the group that left from the
right door or the left door? So actually רש"י Rashi here says,
quotes the earlier רבא Rava and says yes, it would automatically become
מעשר. maaser. Even though you don't know which tenth it is, since
you know it is tenth. the tenth, okay, that is enough to
automatically make that last one מעשר. ma'aser. So now the גמרא Gemara
says ולישני ליה כגון שמנה תשעה וכי מטא עשרה קרי חד מרישא.
v'lishnei lei kegon shemanah tishah v'chi mata asarah kari chad me'reisha. Why
don't you say that you counted nine, וכי מטא עשרה קרי חד
מרישא? v'chi mata asarah kari chad me'reisha?
So why don't you say that here's what happened. You went one,
two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, and then when number
ten came along, you called it accidentally one. You started the counting
over again. Hold on just one second. Let me just double check
this.
Right, you counted it again, and then you went one, two, three,
four, five, six, seven, eight, nine, ten.
So, right, meaning the first nine you counted, then you got lost
in track, like the video that my
dad, I was just thinking about that same little video clip.
Anyway, it's a Monty Python sketch. Anyway, you counted nine, and then
you thought you had counted ten, so you started again. So therefore,
the number ten, right, the nineteenth of all of them would be
the מעשר. ma'aser. It was the only one you counted ten, but
the first nine were exempt because of מנין הראוי. minyan harauy. So
why didn't we have that example? Why did you have to say
this example of nine and nine? Why didn't you give a different
scenario?
So don't call it the ninth, the tenth, or the tenth?
Ah, so Michael is saying, who cares if you call the tenth
number one? We've learned before that if you call the ten nine,
that it automatically is מעשר ma'aser anyway. So that's essentially the answer
the גמרא Gemara says. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
So כסבר עשירי מאליו קדוש. kasavar asiri me'elav kadosh. No, the tenth
one is automatically קדוש kadosh even if you called it one, it
was קדוש. kadosh. Okay, now of course, as I said, what would
you have done if you didn't hold like רבא Rava that the
tenth one is automatically קדוש, kadosh, right? Because we already know if
you call ten nine, it's still קדוש. kadosh. But maybe the גמרא
Gemara assumed, yeah, if you were off by one, then it would
be enough. But if you went all the way not to call
it nine or eleven, but you called it one, maybe it wouldn't
be קדוש. kadosh. And we say, no, this is consistent with רבא.
Rava. רבא's Rava own position is regardless of what you call it,
you call it nothing, or you call it one, or you call
it Fred, whatever you call it, if it's the tenth one out
the door, it's קדוש. kadosh. So you couldn't have given that answer,
so you had to give the answer that they went out of
different doors. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ולישני ליה, v'lishnei lei,
they take out the word בגורן, bagoren, דמנאן זוגות זוגות. d'manan zugot
zugot.
Why don't you give this scenario? They were walking out two by
two, like a Noah story. So you're going one, you know, ones,
twos, threes, fours, and then if they all the way up to
nine came out, and then one one last, the last one went
out. So in that case, they all went out of the same
door, they're all פטור patur במנין הראוי b'minyan harauy because the, but
and there's only one מעשר ma'aser because it only sort of joins
up, you know, with again, you don't know sort of which side
of the line it's on, but at anyway, it only is one
of those groups' ten.
Can you do that?
So that's the question, whether you can do that. We're going to
talk about that more after the משנה. Mishnah. Let's just see the
initial answer of the גמרא. Gemara. כסבר עשירי למנין בהמה הוא קדוש.
kasavar asiri l'minyan behemah hu kadosh. So this is very consistent with
רבא's Rava idea that your counting can't override the reality. At first
point, רבא Rava says is we don't even need your counting. If
something is obviously the tenth, you don't need your counting. The next
thing the גמרא Gemara is introducing now is that your counting can't
even subvert that. If you call ten one, it doesn't matter. If
you count them ones, twos, threes, it doesn't matter. The ones that
you're calling fives are really nine and ten, and one of those
is מעשר. ma'aser. So your, not only is your counting not necessary,
but it can't subvert the reality. And so you don't know, so
that's the משנה's Mishnah going to talk. So then you have מעשר
ma'aser and חולין מעורבין chullin me'uravin and you have to deal with
it as a ספק, safek, wait till there's a מום, mum, but
your counting cannot subvert the reality. Yes.
How does that relate to the idea
of והקדישו, v'hikdisho, you called nine or eleven?
Right. So you can extend the קדושה kedushah to nine and eleven,
but you cannot, right. So that's an important point that David is
raising, right. The point is as we said before and we're going
to say again, this is going to be what's going to take
us till the end of the מסכת, masechet, nine and eleven can
also become קדוש kadosh if you miscount them as ten. So your
calling something ten that isn't ten can extend קדושה kedushah to it.
But something that is ten doesn't need your calling and cannot be
subverted. Okay, so that's the basic point. So now the גמרא Gemara
ends up by saying, אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak, so רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said,
זכאי אמי דרהונא בר סחורה. zakai imei d'Rav Huna bar Schora. רב
הונא בר סחורה's Rav Huna bar Schora mother should get so much
נחת nachas from him. It literally says זכאי אמי, zakai imei, has
such merit. דשני ליה שמעתא דריגלא כשמעתא. d'shani lei shma'ata d'rigla k'shma'ata.
Not only did he defend רבא Rava on the רגל, regel, maybe
that means it was a big public event and he defended רבא,
Rava, רבא's Rava position, but he defended רבא Rava with רבא's Rava
own סברא. svara. Because רבא's Rava own סברא, svara, how did he
defend רבא? Rava? By using the concepts of מנין הראוי, minyan harauy,
nine and nine went out of each door, and explaining why other
answers weren't possible because of רבא's Rava idea that the actual reality
of being the tenth defines it as מעשר ma'aser regardless of being
counted, which is why he rejected other possible answers. So he gave
an answer which רבא Rava was perfectly consistent with רבא's Rava own
approach to these things. Number one about מנין הראוי minyan harauy and
number two about the reality of מעשר. ma'aser. So this issue about
how much can your counting, A, certainly what David said is correct,
it can extend it to nine and eleven. How much can it
subvert number ten? That's what we're going to focus on, continue to
focus on now as we turn to the next משנה. Mishnah. And
of course what somebody could have said was besides the... Michael's question,
what do you do about nine and ten, you don't know which
is which? Okay, there's an answer. What do you do when מעשר
Maaser and חולין Chullin are מעורב זה בזה? Me'urav Zeh Bazeh? But
the bigger question is that you might think that when do we
say the physical reality defines itself, if there's a clear tenth. If
there's not a clear tenth, if nine and ten are walking out
together, there's no objective tenth because you don't know which is number
ten, maybe there it should not happen automatically. Now, it's possible to
say in that case, right, it's possible to say אי אפשר לצמצם
Ee Efshar Letzamtzem that one of them is the tenth, one of
them was a little hair before the other and we just don't
know which is which. But that maybe there actually is an objective
tenth. Okay, now with that question we're going to turn to the
next משנה Mishnah because that really is going to be the dominant
question to the end of the מסכת. Masechet. Yeah.
What does this mean his mother had זכות? Zechut? זכאי. Zakai. Yeah,
to say his mother should be happy.
I know, I know, I was just being a little funny about
it.
What? Yes. What is that, isn't that unusual?
Well, I mean, if there's a general sense
that when we talk about a נפטר Niftar and we talk about
the things that the children do and the descendants do bring merit
to
the father and why the mother?
It's very interesting. Yeah, right, I understand why it's focused on the
mother. Well, that's why I sort of translated it as like שב
נחת, Shep Nachas, like you're thinking about like who really will
appreciate what their son does, you think more about the mother than
the father, I don't know. But it's interesting. אשרי יולדתו.
Ashrei Yoladeto. Right. Exactly. The way I read it was that she
must have been a meritorious woman because she has such a child.
Oh, I see, that's interesting.
Happiness of his mother.
Yeah, I don't know.
But it's not the regular רבן בן עזאי, Rabban Ben Azzai, is
it?
רבן
בן עזאי,
Rabban
Ben
Azzai, right, yeah.
Not the regular.
Right.
I mean, yeah, I don't know. All right, let's take a look
at the משנה. Mishnah. יצאו שנים כאחד. Yatzu Shnayim Ke'echad. Two came
out together. You were trying to do single file, you didn't march
them out in pairs, but two came out together. מונה אותם שנים.
Moneh Otam Shnayim. They take out one of the times, you count
them as two, meaning if they came out as five and six,
don't say five, say five six, even if you're not exactly sure
which is five which is six.
Yes, one point here is that the about the ריגלא Rigla is
that according to the
גאונים, Geonim, שבת דריגלא Shabbat DeRigla is a יארצייט. Yahrtzeit. Oh!
Oh,
that's very nice. They say שבת דריגלא Shabbat DeRigla was when they
observed the יארצייט Yahrtzeit of who passed away the last year.
יום שמת בו אדם גדול שמידי שנה בשנה כשמגיע אותו יום
נקבצים.
Yom Shemet Bo Adam Gadol Shemidei Shanah Beshanah Keshemagia Oto Yom
Nikbatzim. Oh, so שבת דריגלא Shabbat DeRigla doesn't mean רגל Regel at
all? Right, רגלא Rigla just means like the time, the right. I
see. So רגל Regel has nothing to do with the three רגלים,
Regalim, it just means the שבת Shabbat of the יארצייט שבת. Yahrtzeit
Shabbat. Oh, that's very nice. But then it would have been the
יארצייט שבת Yahrtzeit Shabbat of his mother, אמו של בן עזאי. Imo
Shel Ben Azzai.
Okay,
maybe, interesting.
Very interesting. All right. All right. Anyway, thank you. Okay, so יצאו
שנים כאחד, Yatzu Shnayim Ke'echad, two went out together, מונה אותם שנים.
Moneh Otam Shnayim. You call them five and six, you don't call
it five.
מנהן אחד, Manan Echad, accidentally you said five, five and six went
out together and you said five. So what happens? תשיעי ועשירי מקולקלים.
Teshi'i Ve'asiri Mekulkalim. So by the time you get to nine and
ten you're all messed up because the thing you're calling nine is
really ten, and thing you're calling ten is really eleven, right, because
you're off by one. Now, the question is why does it say
מקולקלים? Mekulkalim? We actually have a הלכה. Halachah. What happens if you
call ten nine and eleven ten? The הלכה Halachah is ten is
קדוש Kadosh automatically, as we know, and eleven is also קדוש Kadosh
and eleven you eat as a שלמים, Shelamim, the משנה's Mishnah going
to say. So what does it mean מקולקלים? Mekulkalim? מקולקלים Mekulkalim sounds
like there's no solution. No,
you called ten nine and eleven ten, what you said nine and
ten was ten and eleven, so the הלכה Halachah is they're both
קדוש. Kadosh. So רש"י Rashi says well, maybe that's what מקולקלים Mekulkalim
means. It means it's not as simple as you think, it means
they're both קדוש. Kadosh. But then רש"י Rashi has, but there's two
other explanations, one other of רש"י Rashi and one of תוספות. Tosafot.
The other explanation of רש"י Rashi is if you just got mixed
up when you were at nine, ten, and eleven, fine, it was
a little bit of a mistake and then it has all this
הלכה Halachah continue that we've been saying. But you messed up the
whole counting. What
you called six was seven, what you called seven was eight, what
you called eight was nine, so the whole thing is a mess.
Okay, so therefore now what's the הלכה, Halachah, the whole thing being
a mess?
So anyway רש"י Rashi says that that might throw everything off and
I forget exactly even what he says the consequence of that would
be. Hold on a minute.
הלך לו המנין וכו'. Halach Lo HaMinyan VeChu'.
Yeah, he says that they wouldn't be קדוש ליקרב, Kadosh Lekarev, apparently
that they would be קדוש Kadosh but you couldn't bring either as
a קרבן. Korban. You were so off and everything was so mixed
up you can't call it a מעשר Maaser off by one, it
wasn't even really the tenth. המנין? HaMinyan? המנין? HaMinyan?
Meaning by the time you get to the fiftieth, that's what he's
saying?
No, no, no, by the time you get to the tenth, you
had been doing so many things wrong, you said six when it
was seven, seven when it was eight, eight when it was nine,
that you can't say that this is קדוש Kadosh but it's you
know but you miscalled it by one because the whole counting, the
whole process was wrong, which reminds me of, which reminds me of
that, the בעל המאור Baal HaMaor asks, ראשונים Rishonim ask, we
do two
days... Right, today
is two days or three days because if you that's not a
counting to be off consistently, you know, is not to really count.
So basically, what that would say is you'd not actually do a
process at all of counting. Now again, what would the implication of
that be? Do you think the implication might be you do the
whole thing over again? But רש"י, Rashi, you know, רש"י Rashi doesn't
exactly spell it out, but he suggests that the implication would be
that they're קדוש kadosh but they can't be brought as קרבנות. korbanot.
Anyway, that... well, right, because you mean and the ones that come
after.
You mean after the tenth, not the
eleventh, because you're consistently off. Anyway, that's רש"י. Rashi.
Everything is קדוש kadosh or just...
No, no, no, the ones that were in the ones that you
called ten and the one that was actually ten. Okay, that's the
way רש"י Rashi says it. תוספות Tosafot says that another explanation about
this when you're off. He says actually says תוספות Tosafot says we're
not really sure what happens says תוספות Tosafot if five and six
come out together and you say five. Maybe the fact, and this
gets to this larger issue of whether it goes by the reality
of what happens or by how you designate. When they come out
together and you say five, maybe it should be called maybe that's
five and six, maybe your count doesn't matter, or maybe because you
called it five really they do combine to be five and and
they don't count as two. And because we don't know how to
deal with it now that you've introduced calling two one, everything is
a mess, right? Because everything is a mess, you don't know if
מעשר maaser was מעשר, maaser, if it was nine, if it was
מעשר. maaser. So everything is בספק. besafek. And therefore you have to
deal with it as
בספק besafek according to תוספות. Tosafot.
When you now called מעשר maaser when you now called nine nine
and when you called ten when you said nine and ten and
it was really ten and eleven, there's two possibilities. Maybe we go
by your count and it really is nine and ten and all
you do is you bring number eleven as מעשר maaser or maybe
it was ten and eleven and you bring number nine as מעשר
maaser and number eleven as a שלמים. shelamim. So therefore the whole
thing is בספק besafek according to תוספות. Tosafot. So anyway, those are
three possibilities here and they point to this two important conceptual questions.
One is if you mess up the counting way earlier, how much
does that have a bigger ability to mess everything up? And the
other question is how much do we go by what you said
or by what happened? So one explanation again is that your counting
is completely ignored, it goes by the reality, and when it says
מקולקלים mekukalam it just means, fine, it's like you called nine ten
and ten eleven, it's that normal הלכה, halacha, but then it's a
funny phrase that they're all messed up. The other explanation, two explanations
of רש"י Rashi is that when you mess up the count early
on everything is a mess, and תוספות's Tosafot explanation that we don't
know whether to go by what you said or by what happened
and that also messes everything up because everything is בספק. besafek.
But then according to that, everyone would still agree that if you
didn't mess it up earlier, you just messed up nine and ten
then...
No, because תוספות Tosafot would still say that when they come out
at the same time and you designate it, we might define it
by your designation.
So if I just leave the whole thing open and they all
go out at once essentially...
Yeah, that's
nothing, then there's no tenth. It's only if they're walking out that
you can talk about the tenth.
Okay, anyway, let's take a look. So it says like this: קרא
לתשיעי עשירי. Karu l'shi'i asiri. Now this is the הלכה halacha that
we've been dealing with for a while. You call the ninth one
ten, ולעשירי תשיעי, v'asiri l'shi'i, and ten you called nine. You reversed
it by accident. ולאחד עשר עשירי, V'lachad asar asiri, and you call
eleven ten. So basically you did ten nine ten, okay? Presumably the
reason you did ten and nine is maybe they walked out close
to each other and you got mixed up which was first. Okay,
so anyway, you did ten nine ten. Okay, so it says שלשתן
מקודשים. sheloshtan mekudashim. They're all קדוש. kadosh. The ten is קדוש kadosh
because it's ten objectively, and a nine and eleven are קדוש kadosh
because you called them ten. התשיעי נאכל במומו. Hateshi'i ne'echal bemumo.
The ninth, as we discussed yesterday, cannot be brought as a קרבן.
korban. It was called ten before there existed a ten. So it
does not have the full power of מעשר. maaser. So therefore it
has קדושה kedusha but can't be brought as a קרבן, korban, you
have to wait till it has a blemish. והעשירי מעשר, Veha'asiri maaser,
the tenth is מעשר maaser because just objectively it's מעשר. maaser. והאחד
עשר קרב שלמים. V'hechad asar karev shelamim. The eleventh one is brought
as a שלמים. shelamim. This is what I was saying before. It's
full קדושה, kedusha, it's brought as a קרבן, korban, but it's not
brought as מעשר. maaser. There's only one מעשר. maaser. There aren't two
מעשרים. maasers. Okay, רש"י, Rashi, we're going to learn it in a
minute that there's no such thing as תמורת מעשר. temuras maaser. If
I normally say, and I sort of simplified this yesterday, if I
take a שלמים shelamim and I say תמורה זה, temura zeh, then
they're both brought as a שלמים. shelamim. By מעשר, maaser, if I
stand a מעשר maaser animal in front and I say this is
a תמורה temura of the מעשר, maaser, it doesn't have, I can't
bring it as a קרבן, korban, because there's only one thing to
be מעשר. maaser. You can't have תמורת מעשר. temuras maaser. It's learned
from a פסוק. pasuk. So the eleventh one is not really a
תמורה temura of מעשר, maaser, but because I called it ten and
it came after the ten already existed, it has קדושה kedusha to
be brought as a קרבן. korban. So what's the קדושה kedusha that's
closest to that of a מעשר? maaser? The קרבן korban closest to
that of a מעשר maaser is שלמים. shelamim. It's eaten for two
days and the intervening night. It's קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, it's eaten
by the owners. So it becomes a שלמים. shelamim. That's what happens
to number eleven.
Okay, ועושה תמורה. v'osah temura. Now if you want went ahead and
with this eleven said after the whole process was done, took another
animal, said, oh, I want to transfer the קדושה kedusha from number
eleven to this animal. Now you've transgressed the prohibition of תמורה temura
and the other animal is also קדוש. kadosh. Now the חידוש chiddush
of that is, as we'll see, let's see the response and you'll
see what the חידוש chiddush of that is. דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei
Rabbi Meir. That's Rabbi Meir. אמר amar רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. *Amar
Rabbi Yehuda*, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says, וכי יש
תמורה tmurah. עושה תמורה tmurah *V'chi yesh temurah osah temurah*? How can
a תמורה tmurah *temurah* make a תמורה tmurah, *temurah*? Meaning, how do
you conceptualize number eleven? And this goes back to what I pointed
to you yesterday. Number eleven existed after number ten was already קדוש
kadosh. *kadosh*. And you called eleven ten. And as we said yesterday,
eleven only becomes קדוש kadosh, *kadosh* not only when you call it
ten, but what did you do to number ten? Remember, what did
the משנה mishna *Mishnah* say you did to number ten? You called
it nine. So you basically tried to deny the קדושה *kedushah* of
ten, give that קדושה *kedushah* to eleven, it's very similar to תמורה
tmurah *temurah*. So רבי Rebbi יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says, yes eleven is
קדוש kadosh. *kadosh*, but you know why eleven is קדוש kadosh. *kadosh*?
Because essentially it's a תמורה tmurah *temurah*. It's תמורת מעשר ma'aser *temuras
ma'aser*. Now normally we don't hold of such a thing as תמורת
מעשר ma'aser. *temuras ma'aser*, but that's how he understands why eleven is
קדוש kadosh. *kadosh*. So therefore he says, you can't now take the
קדושה *kedushah* of eleven... תמורה tmurah *temurah* cannot make another תמורה tmurah.
*temurah*. Only the original קדושה *kedushah* can make a תמורה tmurah, *temurah*.
תמורה tmurah *temurah* cannot make a תמורה Temura? *temurah*. So if you
tried to transfer the קדושה *kedushah* from eleven to another animal, the
other animal is not קדוש kadosh. *kadosh* because eleven itself is a
derivative קדושה *kedushah*, it is a תמורה Temura *temurah*. One minute. אמרו
משום רבי Rebbi מאיר *Amru mishum Rabbi Meir*, so then they said
in the name of רבי Rebbi מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, here's the answer
back. אילו היה תמורה Temura לא lo, היה קרב *Ilu hayah temurah
lo hayah karev*. No, you can't call eleven a תמורה Temura *temurah*.
There's no... there's no תמורת מעשר ma'aser *temuras ma'aser*. You're not... you
don't bring as a קרבן korban *korban* תמורת מעשר ma'aser, *temuras ma'aser*.
We learned that out, we'll discuss that when we get to מסכת
תמורה *Maseches Temurah*. So therefore he says, I cannot call it a
תמורה *temurah*. So I have to say that it has its own
intrinsic קדושה *kedushah*. So here is very clearly a simple conceptual question.
Number eleven can only be קדוש kadosh *kadosh* after ten exists and
after you try and if you try to deny the status of
ten. By virtue of what is eleven קדוש kadosh, *kadosh*? Is it
קדוש kadosh *kadosh* based on the model of תמורה *temurah*? I've tried
to remove it from ten and place it on eleven. Or is
it קדוש kadosh *kadosh* because I called it ten and there wasn't
really something else that was ten that I was calling ten that
was enough to give this to see this act of calling it
ten as a type of way of instilling it with קדושה *kedushah*.
Not that it's truly מעשר ma'aser. *ma'aser*, but it's a type of
an act of קדושה *kedushah*, direct קדושה *kedushah*, not derivative, not transfer.
And that even though I called nine ten, but that's not really
competing with eleven because that's not really ten anyway. Okay. So anyway
so that's the debate of רבי Rebbi יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי
Rebbi מאיר *Rabbi Meir*, and basically רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* makes the
stronger point. He says you can't call it a תמורה *temurah*, we
would never say you could bring it as a קרבן korban *korban*.
You don't bring... other תמורות tmurahs. *temurot* you bring as קרבנות korbanos.
*korbanot*, but you don't bring a תמורה *temurah* of מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser*
as a קרבן korban. *korban*. So you can't say that it's a
real תמורה *temurah*. To which רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* might say, okay,
it's not a real תמורה *temurah*, but it's a quasi, you know,
my side of it, it's based on the model of תמורה *temurah*,
it's not exactly the same as a תמורה *temurah*. Anyway that is
their debate with an implication of whether it can make a תמורה
*temurah* and why it can be brought as a קרבן korban. *korban*
to begin with. Okay, so now let's see how the משנה mishna
*Mishnah* finishes. קרא לתשיעי עשירי, לעשירי עשירי, ולאחד עשר עשירי v'l'achad asar
asiri, *Kara l'tishi asiri, la'asiri asiri, leachad asar asiri*, now here's the
case where you did ten-ten-ten with nine, ten and eleven. You did
not change the status of ten. So, you might... so here's הלכה
*halakha*. אין אחד עשר achad asar, מקודש *Ein achad asar mikudash*. Eleven
is not. Because you have to, as we're going to say, זה
כלל zeh klal *zeh klal*, this is the principle. כל שלא נעקר
שם עשירי ממנו, אין אחד עשר קדוש Ein achad asar kadosh. *Kol
shelo ne'ekar shem asiri mimeno, ein achad asar kadosh*. If you do
not uproot the name of ten, if you... you have to you
have to deny ten its status in order to give that קדושה
*kedushah* to eleven. If you've given ten its status and you've called
it מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser*, eleven is now meaningless if it comes afterwards.
You raised an interesting question before, like is there any time we
make you go back, let's say you called everything one, or everything
ten, or one through seventeen, two... Right.
So that's what... we'll see that as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues
to develop. That's probably implicit in רבא Rava *Rava*'s position that the
עשירי *asiri* is קדוש kadosh מאליו *kadosh me'elav*, that it might not
even require, you know, any counting. It's anyway we'll see. I mean
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* said before לא Lo, קרא ען עשירי *lo
kara an asiri*, but what did you do? Did you mentally count
them? Did you indicate? Once you introduce רבא Rava, *Rava* that עשירי
מאליו קדוש kadosh *asiri me'elav kadosh*, it could be that maybe you
don't need any counting as long as they're all walking out single
file. So let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says. Some of this will be sort of suggested by the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. Like a three-year-old count. Right.
Exactly. אמר רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*. So here's what...
so let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now is going
to be... the focus of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to
be exactly along this point about what happens if you do it...
okay, we can't have too many questions now because we gotta get
caught up, gotta be in time for tomorrow's last דף daf *daf*.
Okay, so basically the question about whether you go by what you
say or by what happens. Let's take a look. אמר רבי יוחנן
Rebbi Yochanan, *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, מנאן זוגות זוגות *minan zugot zugot*, if
you count them by pairs, ones, twos, threes, fours as they were
walking out single file, or קנטרין קנטרין *kintrin kintrin*, or by hundreds.
I believe this is from the word century. Okay, your Shai's son
I'm guessing... says that... says it's Greek or Latin...
Okay, but is it basically the same word as century?
I think it's centenarius.
Centenarius, absolute century. Okay, you're counting them by hundreds. Okay, a hundred
walk out at a time, I don't know how you make sure
that they come out only in hundreds. Anyway, עשירי למניינו הוא קדוש
kadosh, *asiri leminyano hu kadosh*. The tenth one is קדוש kadosh *kadosh*
of your counting. Now what does that mean exactly? That's a little
vague. So למניינו מה *leminyano mah*? What does that mean? So there's
a debate about what רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan. *Rabbi Yochanan* meant. רב
מרי אמר *Rav Mari amar*, למניין שלו הוא קדוש kadosh *leminyan shelo
hu kadosh*. You go by your counting. So when the tenth pair
comes out, those are two מעשרות *ma'asrot* coming out at the same
time. And when the tenth hundred comes out, those are a hundred
מעשרות *ma'asrot* coming out at the same time.
All a hundred are קדוש kadosh.
*kadosh*? Yes, because since you go by your counting... Your counting can
define how to group these things. Okay, so even if there's a
concept that the objective reality defines, it's not in complete ignoring of
what you're saying. If what you're saying is wrong, it's one thing.
But you're just grouping them differently. You're grouping them as pairs. So
if you want to group them as pairs, the tenth pair is
two קדוש. kadosh? That's what he says, makes a lot of sense.
רב כהנא Rav Kahana אמר לא, למנין בהמה הוא קדוש. lo, leminyan
behemah hu kadosh. What you say is completely irrelevant. The tenth one
out of the door is קדוש. kadosh. Why? I don't know. So
anyway, some have the גרסא girsa למנינו הוא קדוש, leminyano hu kadosh,
not למנינה. leminyanah. Okay, so anyway, so here's exactly this question. Can
your designation
redefine if it's not wrong, but if it's just regrouping them? תנן,
Tnan, let's see, let's try to see how this works from what
we've taught. יצאו שנים כאחת, מנאם שנים. Yatzu shenayim ke'achat, muna'am shenayim.
Two came out at once, you count them as two. מנאם אחד,
muna'am echad, you count them as one, תשיעי ועשירי מקולקלין. tish'i ve'asiri
mekulkallin. So it's all messed up. So that sounds like we ignore
your counting and we go by the physical reality. בשלמא למאן דאמר
למנין שלו הוא קדוש, Bishlama leman de'amar leminyan shelo hu kadosh, so
it makes sense if you say that we normally go by your
counting, משום הכי הוי תשיעי ועשירי מקולקלין, mishum hachi havei tish'i ve'asiri
mekulkallin, דעל עשירי קא קרי ליה תשיעי, ולחד עשר עשירי. de'al asiri
ka kari lei tish'i, ule'chad asar asiri. So now we understand why
things are messed up, because your counting matters. So therefore, when you
count, what you did is, it's not exactly clear here, but the
point is since we are admitting that your counting actually matters to
some degree, you can't actually go so far to say six and
seven only count as one. That, in fact, presumably, you know, your
counting can't redefine reality, you can group things differently. So we're not
saying we go totally by what you said. But since your counting
matters to some degree, so therefore now you mess things up, because
the thing you called the thing ten, you called it nine, and
the thing eleven you called ten. And therefore your counting also defines
them and the reality defines them and everything is a little bit
mixed up, right? Because now the thing that's מעשר ma'aser is called
nine and the thing that's eleven is called מעשר. ma'aser אלא למאן
דאמר למנין בהמה הוא קדוש, Ela leman de'amar leminyan behemah hu kadosh,
but if we completely ignore what you say, we just go by
the physical reality, לתשיעי תשיעי קא קרי ליה, לעשירי עשירי קא קרי
ליה. letish'i tish'i ka kari lei, le'asiri asiri ka kari lei. So
it didn't really mean קא קרי ליה, ka kari lei, but it
means the ninth is the ninth and the tenth is the tenth.
Meaning the question really here is, you can't say, meaning here's the
simpler way to frame the question. You can't say you totally ignore
what the guy says, because our משנה Mishna says that if you
miscount, nine is ten and eleven is ten, it has an implication.
And if you say you just totally go by the reality, who
the heck cares what you say, even if you say nothing, I
mean even if you say the completely wrong thing. So אמר לך
רבי יוחנן, amar lach Rebbi Yochanan, so רבי יוחנן would say to
you, כי אמינא אנא, ki amina ana, when do I say that
you ignore your counting? It's not really רבי יוחנן, it's the way,
it's the way רב כהנא Rav Kahana explained רבי יוחנן. When would
I say you completely ignore your counting? היכא דאיכוון לאפוקי זוגא זוגא.
Heicha de'ichaven le'apukei zuga zuga. When you're, now this is, if you
ask me, the exact opposite makes sense here. When you're trying to
regroup them, you're trying to regroup them and say I'm counting by
twos, I'm counting by hundreds, then we don't, we don't recognize that
whole thing. We only count by ones. Your whole, your whole attempt
is ignored. Okay, אבל בהיכא דנפק ממילא, aval beheicha denafak mimmela, if
it was an accident, two came out at once, you counted nine
accidentally ten, ten accidentally as eleven, לא, then I don't completely ignore
what you said. Now again, I don't really get that. I would
think that if I am actually consciously trying to redefine, we should
more go by what I'm trying to say. But the גמרא Gemara
says no, if you're trying to redefine, we don't acknowledge any countings
other than by ones. Okay, but if you are counting by ones
and you mistake, so the fact that you're basically playing within the
system and you made a mistake, there's a certain impact to what
you said. Okay, but clearly this is a harder position to defend.
The משנה Mishna makes it say, let's say clear that at least
to some degree what you say matters, and now we're having to
limit it very narrowly to, to cases, you know, where it's only
was a slip-up and not where it was an intentional regrouping. Okay.
So now let's see how the גמרא Gemara continues. תא שמע, Ta
shema, come and hear.
מנאן למפרע, Munan lemafrea, we have a ברייתא braisa that says you
counted backwards, ten, nine, eight, seven, six, five, four, three, two, one.
Okay, does that create מעשר בהמה? ma'aser behemah? So עשירי שבמניין הוא
קדוש. asiri shebiminyan hu kadosh. Yes, the tenth one is קדוש, kadosh.
meaning the one you called number one. So the גמרא Gemara says
בשלמא למאן דאמר למנין בהמה הוא קדוש, bishlama leman de'amar leminyan behemah
hu kadosh, if you say you ignore what you say, you go
by the animals, fine, שפיר, shapir, we understand. אלא למאן דאמר למנין
שלו הוא קדוש, ela leman de'amar leminyan shelo hu kadosh, if you
say that you go by your counting redefined, so why don't you
say that you counted the, called the first one ten? So you
could still say the number one is the tenth of a sequence,
you defined the sequence, but it's still the tenth thing that you
counted. But anyway the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that. The גמרא Gemara
says עשירי קא
קרי ליה חד, asiri ka kari lei chad, you called number ten
one. אמר רבא, amar Rava, אחוה דאיתא במניינא פרסאה. achva de'ita biminyana
parsa'ah. No, because in Persian that means ten.
דקרו לעשרה חד. dekaru le'asara chad. Now, but for them who lived
in Persia, maybe they felt that it had to, some way in
which your number, when you said one, it actually could mean ten.
Yeah, I agree, it's not, it's not the most satisfying answer, especially
because it probably was not what the ברייתא braisa meant. Anyway,
there was,
anyway there was an alternative answer, you could have said that there
it's still... the tenth thing that you counted, which is very different
than when I group them in twos or in hundreds, the tenth
thing that I counted was the tenth group of a hundred. So
here, it might not be the word ten, but it might still
be you can define how you're grouping them. Anyway, here you see
exactly this question. It's the play between, on the one hand, the
משנה Mishna says if you call nine ten or eleven ten it
has an effect. So what you say does matter to some degree.
We have רבא'ס Rava's teaching that the thing that the tenth is
automatically קדוש. kadosh. And the question is, how do you balance what
you're designating and what's happening automatically? And part of it plays out
with this issue about going up by pairs or going up by
hundreds. Are you entitled to regroup them or not? Okay, now let's
continue.
קרא לתשיעי עשירי ולעשירי תשיעי ולאחד עשר עשירי. Kara latishi'i asiri vela'asiri
tishi'i velachad asar asiri. So here's the idea about when you do
ten nine ten, everything is קדוש. kadosh, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. מניין
שאם קרא לתשיעי עשירי ולעשירי תשיעי ולאחד עשר עשירי. Minayin she'im kara
latishi'i asiri vela'asiri tishi'i velachad asar asiri. How do you know if
you did basically this, ten nine ten, ששלושתן מקודשים, sheshloshtan mekudashim, they're
all קדוש. kadosh תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, וכל מעשר בקר וצאן, vechol
ma'asar bakar vatzon, על כל al kol המעשר בקר וצאן, hamasir bakar
vatzon, כל אשר יעבור תחת השבט, Kol asher ya'avor tachat hashavet, anything
that goes under the rod, העשירי יהיה קדש, ha'asiri yihye kodesh, the
tenth one is קדוש. kadosh So somehow because it says any כל
מעשר kol ma'asar means that the concept of מעשר ma'aser. can include
other things. Anything that's called מעשר, ma'aser, even if nine and eleven
are called מעשר. ma'aser. All right, but you'd have everything. יכול שאני
מרבה אף שמיני ושנים עשר? Yachol she'ani marbe af shemini ushneim asar?
Maybe even eight and twelve? If you say once you include nine
and
eleven, אמרת, amarta, הוא קדוש וטעותו מתקדשת. hu kadosh veta'uto miskadash. Look,
מעשר ma'aser. itself is קדוש kadosh, and the error is קדוש, nine
and eleven. מה הוא אינו מקודש אלא בסמוך. Ma hu eino mekudash
ela basamuch. The same way the ten is only קדוש because it's
close to number ten, it is number ten. Right? So it's קדוש
because of its proximity to itself. So אף טעותו אינו מתקדש אלא
בסמוך. Af ta'uto eino miskadash ela basamuch. So those that are קדוש
because of an extension of the idea of מעשר ma'aser. is only
based on proximity to itself. So tenth is קדוש because of its
proximity to itself, it is itself, so nine and eleven means the
proximity to ten. All right, so there's a certain סברא svara that
tells us an error will be קדוש, other things can be מעשר
ma'aser, with their proximity to number nine.
To number ten, thank you.
Was there a סברא svara question it couldn't go more than one
step?
Well yeah, we're gonna that's true also. But here we're talking about
the let's say you just initial automatically you didn't count nine ten,
you just counted eight ten, you know, you total something like that.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
It reminded me of a line from Sherlock Holmes once where somebody
sort of recognizes Sherlock Holmes when he gets off of a train,
he says, "I recognized you by your great similarity to yourself." So
anyways,
the גמרא Gemara says like this. תני תנא קמיה דרבי יוחנן. tani
tana kamei d'Rabbi Yochanan. So a תנא tana prompt, sorry. והתניא, V'hatanya,
מה הוא מיוחד אף טעותו מיוחדת. ma hu meyuchad af ta'uto meyuchadet.
Don't we say the same way it the מעשר ma'aser. is singular,
its error singular, meaning you're only allowed one other thing מעשר. ma'aser,
You can't have both nine and eleven, only the same way there's
only one מעשר, ma'aser. there's only one off-מעשר. ma'aser. There aren't two
things that are, you know, pseudo-מעשר. ma'aser Only one pseudo-מעשר. Mayser תני
תנא קמיה דרבי יוחנן. tani tana kamei d'Rabbi Yochanan. הא מן Ha
man רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון היא. Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon hi. That's
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון. Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon. דתניא De'tanya רבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Eliezer berabbi Shimon omer לעולם אין אחד עשר
קדוש le'olam ein achad asar kadosh עד שישתוק בתשיעי. ad she'ishtok betishi'i.
You have to say nothing by
nine. ויקרא
לעשירי תשיעי
ולאחד עשר עשירי. V'yikra la'asiri tishi'i velachad asar asiri.
And you have to say nine and ten for ten and eleven.
Okay, now we're going to say why. But basically the point is,
yeah, there is an opinion out there that you cannot have nine
and eleven קדוש at the same time. If nine you called מעשר,
mayser, eleven won't be מעשר. mayser. And now we're going to explain
why. Obviously on the face of it the reason is obvious that,
you know, that calling eleven ten is not meaningful unless you've called
ten nine, and calling ten nine is not meaningful unless, you know,
if you've called nine nine or if you've called nine ten. So
you have to skip nine in order that you can call ten
nine in order that you can call eleven ten. So that sort
of intuitively makes sense that only then will the calling eleven ten
be meaningful. But the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to give another explanation. תוספות
Tosafot sort of says what I just said, but the גמרא'ס Gemara's
going to give or I said what תוספות Tosafot said. But now
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. סבר לה כרבי יהודה. savar
lah k'Rabbi Yehuda. So he holds, why does he hold this that
you have to be quiet by nine? He holds like רבי יהודה.
דאמר De'amar טעות מעשר תמורה הוי. ta'ut ma'aser tmurah havei. He holds
like רבי יהודה that when you nine and eleven if they're going
to become קדוש are based on the model of תמורה. Okay. וסבר
לה כאבוה Ve'savar lah k'avuh and רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון Rabbi Eliezer
berabbi Shimon holds like his father רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon דאמר De'amar
אין תמורה חוזר תמורה. ein tmurah chozer tmurah. רבי שמעון בר יוחאי
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai אין תמורה חוזר תמורה. ein tmurah chozer tmurah.
Only one תמורה allowed per animal. Now this is not a תמורה
of a תמורה, it's one תמורה from the original. So therefore if
you made nine מעשר, mayser? you've essentially made a תמורה of the
מעשר. mayser, You can and therefore you cannot make another תמורה of
the מעשר. ma'aser, Do you understand the idea? Your original animal can
only have one thing that's its תמורה. So therefore if it's based
on the model of תמורה, then you understand why you can only
have one thing that is pseudo-מעשר ma'aser because it's only every animal
is only allowed one תמורה and when you get up to number
eleven you've already used up its allotment of תמורות. Okay. So that's
how the גמרא Gemara explains it. Now we go on. אמר רבא
Amar Rava, *Amar Rava* יצאו שנים בתשיעי *yatzu shnayim b'tishii* two came
out in number nine קראן תשיעי *karan tishii* עשירי *asiri* so I'm
sorry קראן תשיעי *karan tishii*. Okay, so basically nine and ten came
out and you said nine because they came out together. So what
have you now done? You've now called nine nine and you've called
ten nine. So what happens when you call ten nine? It's also
מעשר ma'aser, *maaser*, right? Doesn't really matter what you've called it, but
you don't know which is which. So it says עשירי ותשיעי מעורבים
זה בזה *asiri v'tishii m'uravim zeh b'zeh*.
So fine, you have מעשר ma'aser *maaser* and חולין *chullin* mixed up
together. It's actually regardless of what you said. If you don't know
which is which, even if you said nine ten, you have עשירי
*asiri* and מעשר ma'aser, *maaser* מעורבים זה בזה *m'uravim zeh b'zeh*. As
long as you don't know right which one came out first. Okay,
now עשירי מאליו קדוש *asiri meilav kadosh*.
And this is from you didn't even put the the mark on
it, but since you did then then then the mark would extend
to... Well no, but if you
had a ספק *safek* then that would go back to Rava's point.
If there was an objective tenth and you might have miscounted, right?
If you genuinely don't know and you pick one arbitrarily, see that's
what's not clear about this גמרא *Gemara*, you're right. But but if
you really emphasize Rava that עשירי מאליו קדוש *asiri meilav kadosh*, maybe
picking one arbitrarily doesn't help you. It's still מעורבים זה בזה *m'uravim
zeh b'zeh*. You don't really know which one was the עשירי *asiri*.
Yeah, so these two cases contradict the previous statement we said about
how nine cannot be because the ten didn't come yet.
Nine
if you called nine ten, it's קדוש *kadosh* but it can't be
brought as a קרבן korban *korban*.
Oh that's okay.
Okay, so here but here anyway you called both of them nine,
so you didn't call nine ten.
But in the case before רבי שמעון Reb Shimon *Rabbi Shimon's* son,
yes, it could be the תמורה *tmurah* of ten.
It could be the תמורה *tmurah* but it won't be brought as
a קרבן korban. *korban*. I mean he would say that right, that's
true as well, which is in the משנה *Mishnah* you would have
only thought that the model of תמורה *tmurah* was used for number
eleven. Here we're saying that the model of תמורה *tmurah* would even
be used for number nine with the difference that number nine wouldn't
be brought as a קרבן korban. *korban* and number eleven would. That
is correct. Okay, so עשירי מאליו קדוש *asiri meilav kadosh*. In that
case the tenth is automatically, they're mixed up, right? And it could
be even if you designated one as ten although that's not the
case the גמרא *Gemara* said if you really don't know which is
which. Now ותשיעי תשיעי קא קרי ליה *v'tishii tishii ka-kari lei* and
you called the nine nine. So nine was nine and ten you
called nine but it doesn't matter, ten was ten, so they're mixed
up. Okay, now קראן עשירי *karan asiri*, now nine and ten came
out at the same time and you said ten. Okay, because you
knew you were up to ten, but you didn't know which one
to call ten. So then what did you do? You called ten
ten and you called nine ten. So now it's not מעשר *maaser*
and חולין *chullin* that are mixed up, it's מעשר *maaser* and this
קדושה *kedushah* that can't be brought as a קרבן korban *korban*. So
then עשירי ותשיעי מעורבים זה בזה *asiri v'tishii m'uravim zeh b'zeh*. Ten
and nine are mixed up, but meaning nine as a קרבן korban
*korban*, as the קרבן korban. *korban* that can't be brought, right? Because
nine and ten came out and you called both of them ten.
So the מעשר *maaser* is מעשר *maaser* and the nine is something
that was called ten which is has קדושה *kedushah* that can't be
brought as a קרבן *korban*.
So so in the first case what do you do?
You just call them both nine.
No no, what do you do with
חולין *chullin* and מעורבים זה בזה *m'uravim zeh b'zeh*?
You wait for a מום *mum*.
And what do you do with the second case?
Second case you also wait for a מום *mum*. So right, I
guess the difference would be, here's the difference would be let's say
if in the second case if you actually intentionally used it you
could get מלקות *malkus* from misusing קדשים *kodshim* because they're both קדשים
*kodshim*. Also maybe in the first case you could be מקדיש *makdish*
them בתנאי bit'nai *bitnai*. If this is the חולין *chullin* then I'm
מקדיש *makdish* it בתנאי *bitnai* and I'm מקדיש *makdish* the other one
and then you could you know bring them both maybe as a
קרבן *korban*. So there's other possibilities.
But if you called them both nine in the first place and
the next one would be you call ten.
No, if you did then we'll deal with that one when that
happens. Okay, anyway, so in that case מעורבים זה בזה *m'uravim zeh
b'zeh*. מאי טעמא *mai taama*? עשירי עשירי קא קרי להו לתרוייהו *asiri
asiri ka-kari lei l'tarvaihu*, you called both of them ten. So מעשר
*maaser* is מעשר *maaser* and the ninth is a ninth called ten
and therefore has קדושה *kedushah* which can't be brought as a קרבן
*korban*. Okay, יצאו שנים בעשירי Yatzo shenayim b'asiri. *yatzu shnayim b'asiri*, ten
and eleven come out at the same time. וקראן עשירי *v'karan asiri*,
you called them ten. So now you've called ten ten and eleven
ten. So now you have עשירי ואחד עשר מעורבים זה בזה *asiri
v'achad asar m'uravim zeh b'zeh*, ten and eleven but meaning eleven with
this קדושה *kedushah*. So they're both brought as a קרבן *korban*, one
is מעשר *maaser*, one is שלמים shlamim, *shelamim*. What if you don't
know which is which? Which is this case, we'll talk about that
in a minute, but at least you get to bring both of
them as a קרבן *korban*.
But that's only תמורה *tmurah* if you call ten nine.
No, it's if you called eleven ten then it's actually gets to
be brought as a קרבן *korban*.
Even if you labeled ten correctly?
Ah, we're going to get to that, excellent point. You weren't עוקר
שם עשירי oker shem asiri? *oker shem asiri*. Excellent point, we're going
to get to that. Okay, קראן אחד עשר *karan achad asar*, you
called ten and eleven eleven. So עשירי וחולין מעורבים זה בזה *asiri
v'chullin m'uravim zeh b'zeh*. So fine, ten is קדוש *kadosh* anyway automatically
and eleven is not because you called it eleven. So now you
have a מעשר *maaser* and a and a totally חולין *chullin* like
a totally you know non-sanctified animal mixed up. Okay, so all of
that makes a lot of sense except as James said there's a
lingering question here. So גמרא *Gemara* says הא תו למה לי *hatu
lamma li*, why do you need to give me this case about
ten and eleven if you gave it to me by nine and
ten? So גמרא *Gemara* says exactly because of James's point, היינו הך
*hainu hach*, it's the same point as the nine and ten. No,
הא קא משמע לן דכל דבת אחת תרוייהו כקדשי *ha kamashma lan
d'kol d'vas achas tarvaihu k'kadshi*. If ten and eleven came out at
the same time and you said and ten, they both become ten
מעשר *maaser*, ואף על גב דלא נעקר שם עשירי ממנו *v'af al
gav d'lo nekar shem asiri mimenu*, exactly what James said, even though
you did not deny ten its status, but nevertheless because they came
out at the same time they both can be מעשר *maaser*. Why?
Because if conceptually if here's the question about why you have to
deny ten its status in order to make... make eleven קדוש. Is
it a model of תמורה? So if the model's תמורה you have
to be trying to remove from one and place on the other.
That doesn't, so if they came out at the same time, it
doesn't help you; you didn't try to remove from the מעשר and
place it on eleven. But if the reason you have to be
עוקר שם מעשר oker shem mayser is because your calling eleven ten
is meaningless if you've already called ten ten, right? The competition, you've
already designated ten and it's the real ten. So if that's the
reason, because of the competition, if that's why you have to be
עוקר שם מעשר, oker shem mayser, so if they're coming out at
the same time, there's no competition. I'm calling them both ten at
the exact same time, so it's not like it had to compete
against the real ten. You don't know which is the real ten
and they're both being called ten at the same time. Okay, it's
not like I've already designated ten and therefore eleven's status is meaningless.
Okay, so that's exactly the חידוש. chiddush. Yes, if they come at
the same time, you don't have to be עוקר
שם מעשר.
oker
shem mayser.
Unlike nine, because nine has a קרבן stuff.
Yes, and then ten and eleven are קדוש. They're both brought as
a קרבן and we'll get to that very soon. Okay, so let's
take a look. יתיב רב כהנא וקאמר לה להא שמעתתא. Yasiv Rav
Kahana v'ka'amar lah l'ha shma'tata. Rav Kahana was sitting and telling over
this idea about nine and ten coming out at the same time,
ten and eleven. אמר ליה רב אשי לרב כהנא. Amar leh Rav
Ashi l'Rav Kahana. Rav Ashi said to Rav Kahana, "But לא נעקר
שם עשירי ממנו." lo ne'kar shem asiri memenu. He didn't hear the
conclusion. He just came with his question, right? He said, "How come,
how could eleven be קדוש? Ten is, you didn't mislabel ten." ותנן
זה כלל, U'tnan zeh klal, this is a principle, כל שלא נעקר
שם עשירי ממנו אין האחד עשר מקודש. kol shelo ne'kar shem asiri
memenu ein ha'achad asar mekudash. If you don't uproot the name of
ten, eleven does not become קדוש. So he says, הני מילי בזה
אחר זה. hani mili b'zeh achar zeh. So the answer was the
same thing we said, that's if it's sequential where it's competing against
the real ten. אבל בבת אחת, Aval b'vat achat, if it's at
the same time, תרווייהו קדשי, tarvaihu kadshi, they're both קדוש. So the
גמרא says, "No, that can't be, the משנה is limiting itself to
sequential." בזה אחר זה בהדיא קתני לה. B'zeh achar zeh behedya katani
lah. That was explicitly the case in the משנה when it's sequential.
קרא לתשיעי עשירי ולעשירי עשירי ולאחד עשר עשירי אין האחד עשר מקודש.
Kara l'tish'i asiri v'la'asiri asiri v'l'achad asar asiri ein ha'achad asar mekudash.
If it was ten, ten, ten, the eleventh is not קדוש. So
we already have the case of sequential. And then if it says
a general rule, the general rule is meant to apply to cases
beyond the specific case that we gave you. זה כלל לאתויי מאי?
Zeh klal l'atuyei mai? When we say there's a rule after we
said the specific example of ten, ten, ten, we said the rule
is you have to be עוקר שם מעשר. oker shem mayser. So
what's it coming to include? לאו לאתויי בבת אחת? Lav l'atuyei b'vat
achat? Isn't it coming to include exactly this case, that at the
same time also it's, it doesn't work, that you have to be
mislabel ten even if they're coming out at the same time? So
the גמרא says, "לא, not necessarily. לאתויי יצא עשירי ולא דיבר." L'atuyei
yatza asiri v'lo diber. To exclude the following case. What does it
mean to be עוקר שם מעשר? oker shem mayser? Let's say ten
came out and you said nothing, ולא דיבר. v'lo diber. דהא לא
נעקר שם עשירי ממנו. D'ha lo ne'kar shem asiri memenu. That's not
good. If ten comes out, you say nothing, and eleven comes out
and you say ten, that also doesn't work. To be עוקר שם
מעשר oker shem mayser doesn't mean just not to call it ten,
but it means to mislabel it. So זה כלל zeh klal, is
telling you you have to mislabel ten. If you said nothing for
ten even though it's מעשר, then it's too late, it doesn't, wait,
wait, then what happens?
The ten is still קדוש, right?
The ten is קדוש of course and eleven is not. So when
we say you have to be עוקר שם מעשר, oker shem mayser,
when we're saying זה כלל, that's coming to say that it's not
even,
it's not just that you can't call ten ten, you have to
mislabel ten. And if you call it nothing, then it's still too
much of a competition with eleven. And but if it's the same
time and there's really no competition, it didn't already get its status,
then ten and eleven you don't have to be עוקר. oker.
So in that case if we did nothing for ten and called
eleven ten, then the eleventh is nothing?
Eleventh is nothing and the ten is
מעשר. Right. ממילא קדוש. Mimeila kadosh. Okay.
Because also because that competition elevates it to the level of קרבן.
Yes, but only then if you've sufficiently addressed that, the problem. But
because, because of that it's enough to elevate it if you've gone
over the hurdles. If you don't go over the hurdles, then you
get nowhere.
But so now we don't have the, we don't have the hurdle.
If you didn't call it anything?
No, because conceptually,
yes, that's true,
you don't have a competition, no hurdles.
That's exactly the case. That's exactly the case, yes. So that's exactly
what we're saying. So when they come at the same time, because
it doesn't have the competition, they're both קדוש and they're both brought
as a קרבן.
Now I was saying eleven is a קרבן as opposed to nine
because it has that competition we said.
Oh, no, that's an interesting point. You're saying in that case if
it didn't have it, yeah, hmm.
That was our rationale before.
That's an interesting point. It's still true though that nine is even
before it's even in the, I mean if you don't want to
say it that way because that also draws on the תורה. Torah.
It's like nine is before you even get really like to the
פרשה parsha of ten. Once you're really into the פרשה parsha of
ten, calling it ten is more meaningful. But you're right, you're right,
because before I was really dealing a little bit more in a
תמורה model and here I'm saying that the reason nine and ten,
that ten and eleven it both works at the same time is
דווקא davka because it's not a תמורה model.
So that's exactly, you're saying both, both brought as as קרבן. It's
still this separation between, or they both brought as as מעשר?
No, one's מעשר, one's שלמים, shelamim. and you don't know which is
which. So hopefully we will get to that pretty soon. Okay, so
now let's take a look.
We only have a half דף left.
I know, but we're not in control tomorrow, so quiet. Okay, so
the גמרא says like this,
דאי לא תימא הכי, D'ei lo teima hachi, if you don't say
that, הא דתניא יצאו שנים בעשירי, ha d'tanya yatze'u shnayim b'asiri, apparently
this statement that we just had a minute ago, which was who
was the one that that רבא Rava said it, now we're going
to find out it was a ברייתא. braita. So it says you
have to agree to רבא, it was a, it's a ברייתא braita
anyway. It says that if two... they came out in the tenth
ולא קדם אחד מהן את חברו *v'lo kideim echad meihen es chaveiro*
and one was and you know they were exactly the same time
you didn't have a choice וקרא עשירי *v'kara asiri* עשירי ואחד עשר
מעורבין זה בזה *asiri v'achas asar me'uravin zeh b'zeh* you both you
have both קדושות *kedushos* and you don't know which is
which אלא לאו משום דאמרינן דבבת אחת תרוייהו קדושי *ela lav mishum
de'amrinan d'bevas achas travaihu kadoshi* we must say that if it's at
the same time they're both
קדוש *kadosh* so הגמרא *haGemara* says if that if it was just
because of that that would not be a proof why I could
give you I could say that it's talking about a very special
case now the special case we're going to say is not going
to sound at all like the case we just described but okay
הכא במאי עסקינן hacha b'mai askinan, *hacha b'mai askinan* what are we
talking about דקדים חד מינייהו *dekadim chad mineihu* it's not true they
came out at the same time one of them did come first
by like a hair by a nose ואפיק לרישיה וקריה אחד עשר
*va'afik l'reishei v'karya achad asar* and of course for some bizarre reason
the one that came out first you somehow bizarrely call eleven והדר
עייל ונפיק בהדי הדדי וקרינהו עשירי *vahadar ayeil v'nafik bahadi hadadi v'karineihu
asiri* and then they got mixed up and then they're and then
they're both coming out the same time and calling both of them
ten so a very bizarre
case the ברייתא Braisa, *braisa* said they came out the same time
you called them ten and we're saying no no no what really
happened is you called one eleven that came out first which was
really number ten and then and then they got mixed up and
you called them both ten so therefore you called ten eleven and
you called eleven ten and you עוקר שם עשירי oker shem asiri.
*oker sheim asiri* okay fine but that doesn't at all sound like
the case we just
described
והא
לא קדם תניא *veha lo kadam tanya* the ברייתא *braisa* says that
one didn't come out before and you just said that it was
a case where one came out first no מאי לא קדם *mai
lo kadam* what does it mean one didn't come out first דהדר
עייל *dehadar ayeil* it means when in the second time around when
it stuck its head back in then they came out again they
came out at the same time but first one of them had
did stick its head out first וכמאן *v'cheman* and who is this
going like that you
called that we said that you called ten eleven דלא כרבי *delo
k'Rebbi* not like רבי *Rebbi* דאי רבי אמר אחד עשר לא הוי
עקירה *de'ee Rebbi amar achad asar lo havi akira* רבי *Rebbi* says
like this when do we say what counts as mislabeling ten mislabeling
ten is only if you call it nine if you call ten
eleven you haven't really mislabeled it why presumably because it's too soon
calling something eleven before you've got to ten is meaningless somehow calling
it nine although you've already called something nine is not as meaningless
as calling it eleven before you've had a ten okay I think
you can understand that right if you've already had eight before you
call two things nine so you fine it's still you know there
were eight that preceded but to call it eleven before ten is
meaningless so now if we're giving the scenario of mislabeling by calling
it eleven it's not like רבי *Rebbi* okay so הגמרא *haGemara* says
one minute אפילו תימא רבי *afilu teima Rebbi* it can even be
רבי *Rebbi* כי אמר רבי *ki amar Rebbi* when does רבי *Rebbi*
say that if you called it eleven it's not a mislabeling היכא
דאיכא בהמות טובא *heicha de'ika beihamos tuva* it's not because of the
reason I just said the גמרא *Gemara* is going to limit רבי
*Rebbi* when you say eleven is not a mislabeling it's when you
have lots of animals why should that matter דאמי אחד עשר כחד
עשר קאמר *de'ami achad asar k'chad asar ka'amar* when you say אחד
עשר *achad asar* in Hebrew אחד עשר *achad asar* could mean two
things it could mean eleven or it could mean one
ten so if you in your first ten you have fifty animals
are counting and you count and you count number ten you say
אחד עשר *achad asar* we're not going to call it a mislabeling
because what you could mean is this is one of my tens
I know I know it's a very funny but it might not
be what you mean but it really is ten so if you
have to be עוקר שם עשירי oker shem asiri. *oker sheim asiri*
it's not explicit enough of a mislabeling because it's possible that it
really means a ten okay so that's the way now again the
simple explanation of רבי *Rebbi* is just it's too soon to call
anything an eleven but the גמרא *Gemara* says no maybe he means
it's because of this reason so in a scenario where you only
had when you had less than twenty and there weren't going to
be more than one ten then אחד עשר *achad asar* would be
an appropriate
mislabeling so anyway trying to get a mislabeling okay הכא דליכא בהמה
טפי *hacha d'leika beheima tfei* and here you do not have more
animals and now we're going to go on to רבי *Rebbi* so
the basic point
is here
that what do you call it I'm still going to still going
to go on but I just want to sum up this point
is that hold on just wait one
second right so the basic point is before we get to the
רבי *Rebbi* issue again about what counts as a mislabeling do you
have to when they come out at the same time do you
have to be עוקר שם עשירי *oker sheim asiri* and I think
conceptually that's an important question because it tells you what is the
logic of
עוקר שם עשירי *oker sheim asiri* again if the logic of eleven
being קדוש *kadosh* is the תמורה *tmura* model so there has to
be a ten that you're now mislabeling and trying to transfer and
bring to eleven and therefore even when they come out the same
time you would have to mislabel something if however the idea of
why you have to be עוקר שם עשירי *oker sheim asiri* is
because ten presents too much competition with eleven because it's the real
ten then if they come out at the same time there's no
competition and there's no problem so this is the question about coming
out בבת אחת *b'vas achas* and the other important point that we
raised was what does it mean to mislabel if you said nothing
is that enough of mislabeling and the גמרא *Gemara* said no that
is not enough if ten is the real ten and to subvert
its status to give eleven status you have to actively mislabel label
ten. It's not enough not to say anything, you have to actually
assign it a wrong label. Okay, now let's take a look at
רבי's statement.
מאי רבי, Mai Rebbi, what's רבי's statement? דתניא, Detanya, we found in
the ברייתא, קרא
לעשירי אחד עשר, Kora l'asiri achad asar, you called eleven ten, ולאחד
עשר עשירי, and eleven ten, is that considered a עוקר שם עשירי?
אין אחד עשר קדוש. achad asar kadosh, It is not, you have
not been עוקר שם עשירי. דברי רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Divrei Rebbi
Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda. דברי רבי, Divrei Rebbi, excuse me, that's what רבי
says. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר, Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda omer, רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה Rebbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda says, אחד עשר קדוש, it
is קדוש, that is a mislabeling. Yeah, of course ten is, everybody
agrees ten is, and eleven also is, that's עוקר שם עשירי.
כלל אמר רבי, Klal amar Rebbi, רבי said a principle. כל זמן
שלא נעקר שם עשירי ממנו אין אחד עשר קדוש. Kol zman shelo
ne'ekar shem asiri mimenu, ein achad asar kadosh. If you didn't uproot
the ten, its eleven does not become holy. Which fine, we sort
of agree to that. The question is whether eleven counts as an
uprooting. אמר רבא, so רבא said, הכא במאי עסקינן, by the way,
don't always take רבי too broadly that eleven does not count as
a mislabeling. What, what's the case? כגון דאית ליה בהמות טובא, Kigon
d'is lei beheimas tuva, that you have many, many animals. דמנה חד
עשרה קאמר, D'mina chad asira kama, that when you say אחד עשר,
we, it's not a sufficient enough mislabeling because it's possible to interpret
it as one ten. Okay,
so that, and therefore that's what רבי says, but really saying eleven
really would be a mislabeling if there was no other way to
interpret what that word meant. Now let's just read the first introduction
to what we're going to discuss tomorrow, which is now going to
be the practical question. Too bad Charlie isn't here because Charlie always
loves pointing out that, you know, that the way you deal with
the דם dam by מעשר בהמה ma'aser beheima is not the way
you deal with it by other קרבנות. korbanos, And what happens if
you have in your case of eleven and ten, you call them
both ten or whatever, they're mixed up and you don't know which
is which? You bring them both as קרבנות, korbanos but one is
מעשר, one is שלמים. Shelamim Now they're both eaten by the owners
two days and one night. So mostly that's okay, but here's the
difference. שלמים shelamim, you do two throws of blood, מעשר you only
do one. And שלמים, shelamim? the חזה ושוק, chazeh v'hashok, the breast
and the thigh go to כהנים. kohanim. Okay, so what are you
going to do if you don't know which is the שלמים? shelamim
Are you going to do them both two? Are you going to
do them both one? Are you going to give the side and
the breast, both of their, of the thigh and the breast to
the כהנים? kohanim? So basically what you do is you're מחמיר machmir
both ways
and you give by both of them you give the, the, the
chest and the thigh to the כהנים kohanim and they eat them.
But then there's the following problem, is that that thing that is
given to the כהנים kohanim can only be eaten by male כהנים.
kohanim. And, and,
and maybe, you know, at least the גמרא imagines, you know, if
they've got that בית אב beis av or whatever has tons and
tons of meat, it's not necessarily that it's all going to get
eaten within the same, within the requisite amount of time. That's how
the גמרא imagines what a problem could be, is that the thing
that you as the owner should be eating, the breast and the
thigh of the
מעשר, the כהן kohen is now going to be eating. If you
were eating it, you would find people to eat with you, but
with them they have a glut of meat, they might not get
around to eating it. So let's take a look at the implications
of that.
Let's look at the דם. dam. Am I correct that if you're
supposed to do one then you can't do two?
Right, there's a whole debate of what happens about right, do you
do extra? It's a question of whether you prefer בל תוסיף bal
tosif or בל תגרע. bal tigra. Less is more or, you know,
is less better or more is better. But let's take a look,
let's just read that one line and then we'll end with this.
So the גמרא says like this. יצאו
שנים בעשירי. So eleven and ten are called ten, so you have
מעשר and שלמים shelamim mixed up. תני חדא ירעו, Tani chada yeiru,
one says you make them both graze, you wait for them both
to be blemished. ותני חדא יקריבו, V'tani chada yakrivu, you bring them
both as a קרבן. ותני אידך ימותו, V'tani idach yamusu, you have
to let them both die. So לא קשיא, lo kashya, how do
you reconcile? הא דתני ירעו, Ha d'tani yeiru, they graze, רבנן היא,
Rabbanan hi, דאמרי אין מביאין קדשים לבית הפסול. d'amri ein mivi'in kodshim
l'veis hap'sul. They say you cannot allow the, bring any, limit the
possibility that a קרבן might be eaten. So if I were to
bring this, the מעשר, the breast and the thigh would go to
the כהנים kohanim and I should be the one eating it. If
I were to eat it, I'd call my family and friends and
we'd have a barbecue and it would get eaten. But if the
כהנים kohanim are getting the breast and the thigh, they have this
glut of meat, they might not wind up eating it. So I
am potentially risking, you know, some of the קרבן not being eaten
because I'm having to play it safe and give it to the
כהנים. kohanim. So I'm not allowed to risk that and I let
them graze and I blemish and I eat them outside the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash with the blemish. Actually the ones that's a שלמים
then have to do a redeem it בתנאי and the way I
fix it. And let's just read one line of the top עמוד.
amud. והא
דתני יקריבו, V'ha d'tani yakrivu, you bring them both, רבי שמעון היא,
Reb Shimon hi, דאמר מביאין קדשים לבית הפסול. d'amar mivi'in kodshim l'veis
hap'sul. That's רבי שמעון who says I don't care, you're better to
bring them both as קרבנות and you run a little bit of
a risk, but you hope that the כהנים kohanim will get around
to eating it and you bring them both as a קרבן.
And we will leave it for tomorrow to find out the idea
about why the position that you have to let them both die,
which seems to be the most radical one, we will leave, we
will find out more about that when we finish tomorrow.
Thank you very much for today.
What? Thank you.